hello we're back with Samuel ner
Jonathan Larson and Peter Wade
discussing active inference djl staying
with the active inference plus Julia
theme thank you all for coming on and
sharing this work so looking forward to
[Music]
it hi everyone it is a pleasure to be
here so like Daniel said we'll present
um a new package for doing active
influence simulations but also for
applying it to data in
Jia and we will leave time for questions
at some moments during the presentation
and then sometime in the end
additionally um we're three people
because we've been working on this
together so we'll alternate a little bit
with the
the all right let's work the first uh
it's nice just to mention who we are so
we're all at o University I'm a PhD
candidate and Sam and Jonathan are
students who have been working on
developing this package with me and we
all come from computational cognitive
science specifically it's called
cognitive modeling you Model Behavior
with competition models and of course
within that specifically predict presing
models H including active influence
models and that's why we made this
package
um and we use this in the context of
competition Psychiatry for clinical
questions and also more broadly for just
modeling behavior and this package is
part of a somewhat larger um process of
project of
developing a software for these kinds of
research questions in
Julia and I'll start with just giving a
brush up on what cognitive modeling is
in general so some members of the
audience might be familiar with this but
others might not um just to set the
stage
for an introduction to active inference
you all have seen this before so we'll
go through it briefly but it's nice to
have this finger tips then we'll get to
the meat of the matter which is of
course how to do this specifically in
code with active inference JL and both
simulating behavior and also fing into
data and finally if there's time we have
somec
and some future work that we'll be happy
to spend some time we might skip that as
well all right cognitive modeling or
computational cognitive modeling um
comes out of psychology C to science
where the main question in those fields
is to find out what are the mental
mechanisms that makes us do the things
we do and so the classic perception
action Loop we have to pick here people
maybe be familiar with that too it's
going be our AC book where you have some
agent which could be a person but it
could actually also be an animal or even
an organoid or even a simulated um thing
system that receives inputs from its
environment and takes actions that
changes its environment and we are here
interested in essentially and I don't
know if you can see my cursor um but
essentially the relation between those
observations and the actions that are
created so basically the
part um after the observation error ends
and before the action error
starts and um traditionally in
Psychology and cognitive science this
been done experimentally so um you take
people out of natural situations and
controlled laboratory situations where
you measure well you you control both so
you decide what they observe and you
measure what they do and so the kind of
classical example of this is have a
computer screen you show people some
image or something maybe you're asked
them to classify them or predict what's
going to happen and you measure what
they do and then you have a measurement
of inputs and measurements of
outputs and you then create some theory
that will make some prediction as to how
they would
made and of course this is a big field
you might have theories of personality
types where you predict that
actions will change faster depending on
inputs there's theories of reinforcement
learning
Etc and so importantly here we're using
already Natural Science approaches
experimental approaches with
quantitative analyses but still with
purely
conceptual theories so the theories are
not formal as they are from are let's
say physics you have mathematical
theor and the trick is often to go from
some conceptual Theory to a Quant
prediction that you can then
test and
specifically give me a moment
here sorry about
that and
specifically as many people know there's
been a what's called a replication
crisis in Psychology and cognitive
science where the whole issue is that
the experiments don't replicate and
that's part of due to statistical
methods issues but also partly due to
problems stemming from the fact that our
theories are not um clearly formulated
so one sentence that's saying that there
is social learning might mean many
different things and so um a Recon
attempt to address them is to move into
formal theories just like in physics so
computational models of this again
relation between observations and action
um and and this is inspired by physics
so in physics people are no strangers to
having things they can
observe in our case it's the behavior
but in physics it can be let's say
radiation from the Sun and then trying
to make inference about something you
can't obsorb in now case the mind and
this cases perhaps the molecules of
the of the
Sun and so the methodology is exactly
the same create mathematical equations
that will describe how CS evolve over
time given observations in the
environment and test them on how well
they describe empirical
collected actions observations and here
I just put on one of the very classic
cognitive models which is the scholar
wagna where you have some very very
simple equations that describe how
actions depend on the observations in
the previous time step with some
learning and a classic learning dat and
that's to say that the many the first C
models were very simple in a few
equations you would kind of describe
these
Rel I think primarily in three Fields is
this approach used where you have some
person or some system and you want to
find formal models of its behavior and
that's in computation Psychiatry where
you want to use it to understand
psychiatric conditions mathematical
psychology which traditionally has been
broader it's essentially the same
questions but a different community and
different types of models used but also
broader just behavior in general not
specifically Psychiatry and
competitional Neuroscience where you
want to relate these
um models to for example neurobiological
processes that could
Implement and they also overly like a
overlap with artificial intelligence and
Eng engineering and so on
where all right so I think a primary use
case especially in our field of active
influence is theoretical simulations
where you just take some phenomenon
let's say learning or let's say learned
helplessness you create a
simulation that can do that uh create
that kind of behavior and you suggest
this as a proposed mechanism of how that
behavior comes about you can use this
for one agent doing one type of behavior
or you can use it for many and then
you're doing agent based models uh
specifically cognitive agent based
models where you rely on actual theories
to but you can also apply it to
behavioral data
and here you're often trying to either
find out what
mechanisms provide actually observed
data you might want to distinguish let's
say clinical populations from each other
and what's called computational
fingerprinting you might also use
results here to inform future theortical
simulations so you can have abms where
every agent has perative values you
found an experiment and you can also use
this to design future experiment where
you use simulation to make sure that
your experiment design will give you as
good results as
possible and finally you can also apply
these approaches in machine learning and
engineering and here of course you can
make robots that use cognitive models
that people might also use in the way
that in general technology and knowledge
of biological systems have always work
with each other so in the same way you
might be inspired how to build a plane
by looking at a bird you might also be
inspired on how to build an image
recognizer by looking at human
being our packages specifically Target
the application to behavioral
data so they can do theoretical
simulations and also in principle be
used for engineering purposes but we've
optimized them for this situation where
you have participants you put them in an
experiment you get behavioral data and
you use those models to understand that
data and that's um what distinguishes it
from some of the other software tools
that are present um so PP now has this
capability also and but otherwise many
of you and there is in the metlab SPM
software also some ways to apply to data
otherwise the focus has often been on
thetical simulations or on machine
learning and if you look at packages
like RX and fur which is incredibly
powerful and well made um that also at
least to my understanding focuses more
on the machine learning engineering part
where the ultimate goal is to use these
models to build tools that can do things
um or maybe for simulations but not to
specifically appli to
beh all right um and I'll just give a
sense of what the workflow here looks
like because if you come from
theoretical simulations or engineering
this might seem really well to start off
designing hypothesized models for how
people
work you then check these models before
applying them to anything but whether
they are worth applying so you do what's
called parameter recovery and model
recovery where you first simulate
Behavior with some parameters you then
estimate those parameters and you see if
you can actually estimate the real
parameters if you
can't recover parameters that you know
are true you can't trust this in when
appli to real
data and also prior and posterior
predictive checks where you just check
that your model can actually generate
the kind of data that you might see in
an experiment and if you can't it's also
not where the clients will be able
then you fit it to data which means uh
finding out what parameters of my model
what they must have been to generate the
data that I did so In classical models
it would be learning rates we ask oh
this person adapted this fast so his
learning rate must be this and this in
the context of active influence it's
usually um parameters of the generative
model the a matrix and B matrices for
example that we want estimate and
finally we can also estimate how well
the model fits our given given data
because some models might describe some
data better than others we might want to
use this to
select we use this to relate parameter
estimates to some measure that's a cross
participant often this is clinical
populations we might say our learning
rates or are a matri parameters
different between clinical populations
but it might also be relations to let's
say age or psycho pharmacological
interventions
you can also relate it to within
participant things let's say
physiological correlates and could be
pup dation Etc but the primary use case
of course is neurer Imaging where you
say oh according to my model he now this
participant now has a high prediction
error do I see a difference in brain
activity at this moment compared to when
he has low prediction
error this often to find out what the
neurobiological implementation of the
computations of think people
do and finally um you might compare
models and ask questions like which of
these hypothesized models are the ones
that best describe the data and
therefore perhaps the actual
mechanism within people and so you could
compare an active inference and re
enforcement learning model or let's say
two active inference models with
different generative models
inside finally it's worth mentioning
that fitting this to data there are many
different approaches
um broadly speaking they are basion and
frequency to methods they have different
advantages and disadvantages we usually
use basan approaches and that's a long
discussion of why that's nice they
propagate uncertainty they're good you
don't have so much data but I W go into
that just to say that there are also
other ways to fit models to
data and within basion methods because
you can't do exact base to fit them
there are also approximations one
classical approximation is very
methods where you choose some arbitrary
distribution we call it q and you make
it be as similar as possible to the true
posterior belief about the so the
optimal parameter estimate you do this
by minimizing a variational re energy
and as it happens that's also what
active INF agents
use another in cognitive modeling widely
used method is sampling approaches like
Mark of chain C there are also others
where essentially you try out many
different parameter values and for each
of them you calculate the likelihood of
that value you do this in a smart way
but it still takes a long time and you
get a full estimate of the probabilities
of different par
[Music]
values they have different claims to
being useful for different um use cases
so assembling is good um for parameter
estimates but they take a long time they
might Nota work varation base has some
claims to being a better estimate of
quality of fit or model evidence there's
a whole few where people are still
writing
and if anyone's interested we can take
questions on that but importantly the
tools we make here can do either these
two finally it's just worth mentioning
that we as researchers use ban methods
to understand people's behavior but
within active influence we also theorize
that people use basian methods to
understand the world
it's nice to keep those separate so we
might use a sampling approximation to
Patient influence to fit our models to
data but still believe that people use
variational Bas to understand their
environment and so in the following when
we talk of generative models we're not
talking about our model of people we're
talking about people's models of the
world and again do ask questions that
that's one of the tricky points
sometimes when we're doing this what's
called metapas
good there are many paradigms within
cognitive modeling mathematical
psychology have many many ways of
modeling often specific behavioral tasks
there are these old cognitive
architecture models actr and sore are
biggest ones where people also trying to
do unified models of behavior in general
which rely on very different assumptions
than active inflence and often we're not
aware of them perhaps we should be so
I'll just bring up here and they are
kind of raw old school computationalist
models different modules interacting
there of course reinforcement learning
models where you assume that par people
do actions get rewards from their
environment and try to find actions that
maximize those rewards there many others
like deep learning models Etc and but of
course today most relevantly there are
basian mind models you think that
people's minds use ban influence of some
sort to understand the
[Music]
there are many schools of Bas mind
models might look at just ten Bound for
a different School than ours but active
inflence specifically belongs to a
variational ban mind model we use
variational approximate basian inference
as a model of how people
work and this has close ties to
predictive coding and predictive
processing so broadly speaking we might
call this rational basan predictive
processing models they can be just a
perception like harion filters or
plenty of models out there or they can
include action as well and when they
include
action it's called active INF so
variational Vision predictive processing
models of perception and action is
active and and now we'll give an
introduction to that but we'll leave
time for one question before we move on
are there any
questions here I'll ask one maybe you'll
revisit it later to aun
asked what's the biggest challenge you
faced building this
package that's a long and Technical
discussion I think the main thing is
that in Julia there are many ways of um
doing what's called the auto
differentiation which is a technical
thing that you need to do the the
parameter estimation and there's just a
whole ecosystem of packages doing that
and we've had to become very familiar
with those to find the ones that work
the best and and that's not an easy TK
the part of the package is to hide that
from the user so they don't have to
engage with
it I don't know if you agree with
that probably yeah we can revisit it
okay all right one more question just
while we're while we're pause Frasier
asked is there anything in active
inference JL that is particularly suited
to compositional agents or collectives
kind of leading you into your paper I
know so I'll return to that in the end
if we have time but um
basically you can use the same method
that we use to make inferences about a
given human participant in an
experiment on instead of a human
participant you can use it on a
simulated Collective and treat that
Collective as if it that is also doing
some kind of cognition or active
inference at least which is of course
fundamental to active inference in
general we expect a cell to do active
inference but also person and also
Collective and so if we treat a
simulated Collective as let's say a
foreign system that's doing something we
don't know what is we can fit a model to
that in exactly the same way we do to a
person and make inferences about let's
say the parameters of that simulated
collectives D model of the mind and in
the end time I'll just show like results
from that paperwor we do exactly this
just demonstrating it examp that's an
exciting question
obviously all right all right I will
just briefly uh touch on the software
ecosystem um that we build the package
in um so firstly why jya uh it's fast
and it's very intuitive meaning that if
you come from python or madlab you can
carry a lot of the same inations um over
into Julia and then it has a community
that is growing quite fast of people
doing data science machine learning and
Caron modelings we're doing then Julia
is natively auto differentiable which
means that you don't need to have a back
end in another language to do auto
differentiation uh which makes it very
fast in Julia for this there's a very uh
nice package package called touring. JL
uh which is just a package for
probabalistic programming in general and
it can do both uh sampling methods such
as mcmc or no uturn sampler um and and
variational inference uh as well then in
Jula there's also a sister package to
active inference which takes different
kinds of cognitive models and make it
very easy to fit data and to those kind
of models uh by kind of like wrapping
touring uh and that's where kind of like
our active inference JL package comes
into um play as this is a cognitive
model that through action models can be
used uh to touring to fit uh data quite
easily and we'll show
later in the presentation as
well then we'll just briefly touch on
some of the core elements of active
inference uh with regards to perception
action and learning so for the
perception part this is uh the
minimization of the quantity variational
free energy where we through this uh
minimization we can infer States
optimally based on observations and
there's different kinds of variational
inference or sorry different kinds of
algorithms um that we can use to do this
uh I'll later go into the specific
algorithm that we're using uh in this
package then we have action and active
inference which is Guided by the
minimization of a quantity called
expected free energy and this can have a
have a lot of different kind of
Expressions if you look at the ones that
we show here in the slide we have one
that's Information Gain versus pragmatic
value which is basically where you get
the Explorer exploit behavior for free
in active inference which is really nice
um and then we also use uh the expected
free energy to calculate a posterior
probability over policies
uh where policies are actions so this is
kind of like the quanti that we use to
kind of like guide the action selection
uh we're also going to go into that a
bit later then we have learning in
active inference this is uh specifically
for categorical distribution beliefs so
there's other ways of learning for
continuous um cases however here we take
it for categorical
distributions uh for this we use derish
lay Prius over the generative model
parameters this is basically derish lays
they have concentration parameters that
we can then add counts to and this is
the update equation that we show here
where we have an Omega which is the
forgetting value times current
concentration parameter and then you add
the new here is the learning rate and
then you then add the kai which is the
data observed and in this sense you just
add counts to the concentration
parameters and then through normalizing
it uh it becomes your new updated uh
generative model parameter um we will
come back to how that's implemented in
the package as well and then uh a quick
refresher on partially observable Market
decision disas so we just want to make
sure to say that this is one type of
generative model uh in active inference
there's other types of generative models
as well and uh pmps they are not active
inance
specific um in the sense you can also
use it in other Frameworks um and then
this uh what we have done in this
package is a discrete State space uh
implementation of pmps you can have
continued Stace space implementation of
pmpd uh pmpd is the mov element of it
though is that the time steps they are
discreete and not continuous um so we'll
just briefly go over conceptually uh the
different parameters in the pmdp and for
this uh we have created sort of like
this little um toy environment uh to
explain this and if you can see this
thing here where you kind of like if you
imagine that it's a dial uh where we can
spin it in different ways uh and then
the goal is to get state three on top in
the little rectangle um so then you have
three action you can spin
counterclockwise clockwise or you can
just make it stay in place which you
would do if you have uh state three on
top for example um but we'll start with
the observation State likelihood model
basically what this encodes is the agent
beliefs on how States generate
observations so it's a categorical
distribution where each column uh has to
sum up to one so in this state uh in
this case as we have a identity Matrix
uh this indicates that the agent can uh
determine istically infer uh the state
based on the observation so if the agent
observes observation one then it will
infer that it is in state one and this
can be more or less entropic in the
sense we could also have a completely
uniform uh column where we just have 3.3
for all of these and then the agent
wouldn't be able to infert the states
based on the based on the
observation all right so this was the
observation State liih model then we're
going to go to the state transition liih
model and this is basically how the
agents believe beles that the states
change over time um so in this case I've
taken the example of doing it for the
action of going counterclockwise because
this is usually dependent um on actions
so here we see that for example if the
agent is in uh State one and it does the
action spin counterclockwise then it
believes that the next state it's going
to be in uh is going to be state two and
the same if it's in state two then it
believes that it's going to be in state
three um so that's the state likelihood
uh transition model then we have the
prior preference and so this is
basically where we kind of like get to
encode uh kind of like the preferences
or the goals of the agent Um this can be
done both Over States and observations
but in our case we have done it for
observations and this is the case in our
package as well so here for example for
observation one we have encoded a
dislike uh for this observation which is
coupled to the state one and then for
observation two we have neither dislike
nor preference and then for observation
three which is uh coupled um to state
three which is kind of like the goal
that we want we have set a preference
and this is important uh as this kind of
encodes the pragmatic value um which is
then part of the calculation of the
expected free energy as you can see here
below um yes and that's the C parameters
then we'll continue to the D parameters
which are basically just the agents
initial belief at time one uh which
state is it going to be in and here we
just encoded to be certain that it's
going to be in state one then we have
the prior over policies you'll just uh
quickly introduce the notion of policies
where policies are collections of
actions that can have a specific L
length determined by the policy length
which is basically how long in the
future how many time steps in the future
should the agent uh plan so for this
case we only have one time setep in the
future which is why we only have the
three actions here and this is also
sometimes described as the agent's kind
of habits meaning that it has a
preference for certain actions in this
case we have given it a uniform
distribution meaning that the agent
doesn't really have any preference over
uh any policies all right so now that we
have the generative model down uh I'm
going to show you how to implement this
in our package um and we're going to do
this um by providing a worked example of
a teammates environment where the agent
is going to learn the reward probability
in the arms and for this I'll just
quickly have to introduce the notion of
factors and modalities so factors uh are
basically different kinds of States so
in this case it would be we have
location States and we have reward
condition states where reward condition
states are whether the left arm or the
right arm is going to provide the reward
then we have modalities um modalities
are basically different kinds of
observations um so here we have a
location observation we have a reward
observation and we have a queue
observation and I'll go into these uh
when we get to Define them uh in the
generative model to start using our
package you can just add it from the
Julia registry using the Julia package
man manager uh as shown here um
basically for this code you can run
through it uh by yourself and it should
be able to run um then we initialize the
package and we also import the
environments module which is important
uh for the teammates environment that
we're using as an example here and then
we initialize the tmas environment and
here we just set a 95% probability of
providing reward in the reward condition
arm so now we can create uh the actual
generative model uh the pmdp generative
model and you can do this manually by
yourself um but then you have to make
sure that the generative model
parameters are typed in the correct
manner uh which is shown here where it
have to be vectors of rays for ab and
vectors of vectors for c and d and
Vector of floats for E uh it's very
similar to object arrays in numpy
however we have created a helper
function that makes this uh a lot easier
and so I'll just quickly go through the
arguments that the helper function uh
takes so the first argument um is um the
number of states in each factor um so
remember we had two factors we had the
location State factor and the reward
condition Factor where we had in the
location factor we had four states we
had the sense the Q location and the two
right arms so that's four and then we
have two reward condition States reward
condition right and reward condition
left um so we take this as a vector and
give it uh to this function as the first
argument um then the second argument is
the number of observations in each
modality so we have uh four we have
three different modalities in this case
where we have four observations in the
first modality the location modality we
have the location sensor Q and The Arms
then we have uh the second modality
which is the reward modality it has
three observations it has the
observation of no reward reward and loss
uh um then we have the last observation
modality which is the cure observation
modality this we also take as a vector
and give to the function as the second
argument the third argument is a number
of controls for each of these factors so
we have two factors the location factor
and the reward condition Factor um we
only want the agent to be able to
control the location factor so it can
move freely uh between the locations but
in the reward condition State Factor it
shouldn't be able to control what arm
should be the reward arm and so
therefore we just give it one in this
case then we have the policy link which
I have described before it's how many
steps in the future does the agent plan
and then we have uh the fifth and last
argument which is the initial fill which
basically says like when we have cons
when we have made the structure of these
turn to model parameters uh what should
be the initial filling of these and here
it takes both uh it takes zeros which we
have chosen in this instance and then
also takes the argument random which is
nice for testing and uniform uh which is
the default
uh in this case good so now we just uh
having created uh this helper or these
generative model parameters we just need
to fill them with the appropriate values
so we'll start out uh with the
observation State likelihood model and
remember this is the one that encodes
the agent beliefs of how States
generates observations and then infers
States based on the observations it
receives so in this case we have the
location OBS observation which is not as
interesting to us um basically it's an
identity Matrix meaning that the agent
just infers the correct State because we
have encoded to do so um and then we
have two matrices here because we have
for each of the location states which is
one Matrix and then we have two uh
matrices one for each reward condition
State Factor um if you go to the second
modality which is the reward uh modality
this is the one that is interesting to
us because if you look at the First
Column and the last column this is the Q
and Cent location we see that it expects
that these are going to provide the
observation of no reward however for the
second and third column which are the
right and left arms uh we see that in
the second uh row that it has a 50%
chance uh that it believes that this
state is going to produce a reward
observation and then if we go to the
third row we see that it has a 50%
chance of generating this or the agent
believe that there's a 50% chance of
generating this observation so in this
sense the agent doesn't know which of
the arms is going to provide the reward
observation and this is the the modality
that we want the agent to learn we
wanted to approximate the actual reward
probabilities in the tmas environment
then we have um the Q observation
modality which basically just tells the
agent that only when it's in the Q
location does it uh correctly get an
observation that informs it on the
reward condition state of the
environment um and then we're going to
add uh a prior over a and this is where
the learning part comes in um the prior
over a um is the dlay distribution and
the way that we create this is basically
just that we copy uh the structure of a
and then we add a scaling uh
concentration parameter which basically
says that these counts in the DeRay
distribution if they are very high like
if we give it high scaling concentration
parameter each uh new data observation
is not going to matter as much if we set
the scaling uh concentration parameter
low then each data observation we have
is going to going to matter a bit more
and then it's important to say that and
this is bit clunky but uh this is now
going to define the a matrix so the uh
the prior over a is going to define the
a matrix meaning that the a matric that
we just made is not going to be exactly
used however we used it as a template to
create the prior over the
a um great so now we have the
observation State likelihood model now
we need to encode the state transition
likelihood model and this is uh the
matrices for the first uh Factor the
location factor and basically we just
note here that we have rows that are
filled with ones meaning that from
wherever the agent is for that action it
goes to that place that it wants to go
to um and then we have the second uh
factor which is the uncontrollable one
um which is the reward condition factor
and basically this identity Matrix just
tells the agent or the agent believes
that the reward condition State uh
doesn't change uh over time that it
stays the same good so now uh we come to
an interesting parameter which is the
prior preference over observations so
we're we have a vector here for each of
the modalities however the one that we
are interested in is the reward
observation so in this case the first
index is the index of the observation no
reward and we said no preference or
dislike for this the second index is the
uh observation of reward which we said
to have a preference for that it wants
the reward and then we have the third
index which is the uh loss observation
which we set a dislike
for yes and then we continue to the D uh
parameters uh where we have a vector for
each of the factors we have the location
factor um where we basically tell it
that it's going to start the first index
is the center location then we're just
telling it that it it's going to start
in the center location and then for the
second factor which is the reward
condition Factor we just have a uniform
distribution meaning that the agent does
not know what the reward condition uh is
going to be good then we have the last
of these parameters uh which which is
the prior over
policies and we're just going to hear
provide it with a uniform U prior so
this means that as the E parameters are
the habits uh it's not going to have uh
any habits in this case we see here that
we have 16 different policies because we
have a policy length of two and we have
four actions so the total number of
combinations of these two actions is
going to be 16 um and then as said we
just give it a uniform distribution over
these um
policies good so now we're almost ready
uh to initialize the acted inference
agent before we do that we have to
specify some settings um and I'll just
briefly go into these what they do uh
the policy length we have talked about
the use utility uh basically means
should we include the C parameter
preferences that we just said and we've
said this to true then we have the use
States info gain which basically says
that in the calculation of the expected
free energies which is going to guide
action um should we include the expected
Information Gain and then we have the
used parameter info gain uh setting
which basically says that when we
calculate the expected free energy
should we include the expected learning
or updating of the generative model then
we have action selection which which can
take two values either stochastic or
deterministic um I'll go into what they
do when we come to the function that
actually uses the setting then we have
modalities to learn um which basically
specifies what modality do we want the
agent to learn um in our case we want
wanted to learn the reward observation
modality so we specify this by giving it
two we also have factors to learn uh
this is only relevant when we're doing B
and D Matrix learning so it's not going
to be relevant in our case then we have
the fix Point iteration number of
iterations and the fix Point iteration
uh tolerance which is basically saying
that um when should the inference
algorithm stop so you can set it to
either as we do here after 10 iterations
or when the difference between
iterations are equal to a lower between
this threshold
yes the last thing that we need to
Define to initialize the agent is the
parameters here I'll just briefly go
over what they do the gamma is an
inverse temperature function on the
expected free energies uh then we have
the alpha which is inverse temperature
on the action uh selection and then we
have the learning and forgetting rates
uh for the priors over a b and d uh
parameters which are the ones that we
currently have learning for the ones
that we are interested in at the moment
though is the prior over a uh which is
the learning rate and forgetting rate
for this which we're going to set to its
default value of one and the the values
here are all the default uh values good
so now we can initialize our active
inference uh agent by providing it with
the generative model and the settings
and these
parameters and we're almost ready for
the perception and action Loop in itself
and before we do that uh we just have to
specify how many iterations does this
Loop need to contain and then we re at
the teamas which just gives the agent
like an initial
observation and this is the perception
action learning uh loop and it has five
functions and I'm going to go through
them and just briefly explain how they
relate to active inference um so the
infast states function is the one that
actually does the minimization of the
variational free action uh the
variational free energy um and this is
the perception part of active inference
um here in our package we use an
algorithm called fixo iteration also
known as coordinate Ascent variational
inference um and here we also just uh we
provided a picture of an observation
where you can see that we have these
three observations the location
observation reward
observation um and the Q observation
then we have the infer policies uh this
is the one that actually calculates the
expected free energies and it's affected
by uh the settings that we talked about
before uh and the gamma and the E
parameter
it Returns the expected free energies
and it also returns uh the posterior uh
over policies which is and it's this
posterior probability that we are going
to be sampling from when we are sampling
actions um so basically this function
sample action uh just samples from this
posterior probability over policies um
and it is affected by the action
selection where it could be either
stochastic or deterministic if it's
stochastic it just samples from the
probability distribution but if it's
deterministic it all always takes the
policy with the highest
probability then we have the update a uh
which is where the learning occurs and
this is where we basically add the D lay
counts uh to the prior over a and then
it updates the a by normalizing the
concentration
parameters then we have the step teamas
which is basically just the agent
interacting with the environment and
then it provides uh the observation uh
for the next iteration uh in the
perception action learning Loop um so
this is the the loop um and this is the
one that's is also going to be used uh
in the model fitting part um and we are
I think we're taking some questions now
one question one question one question
yes okay I I'll ask one question from
Tintin in the chat they wrote hello
thanks all for this great work have you
implemented basian model reduction or
incremental model construction
structure learning with active inference
JL rather than manual
construction no that's the short so U
the package is just now ready for
deployment and there's many ways to
extend it which we work on but also I
mean if people are interested in
collaboration to develop the package it
will also be one thing so this is
exciting for two reasons like in two
ways by the way um basically model
structure learning it can either be
model structure learning from the
perspective of the
agent learning the structure of the
environment but it can also be model
structure learning from the perspective
of us researchers wanting to find out
what kind of structure a given agent
Hason and and both of these
purposes something we we would like to
do I I think a useful um kind of
connective tissue question where would
you put active inference JL in
relationship to pmdp does in Python and
what RX infer does in
Julia so pmdp was originally um a port
of the SPM functions into python
brilliant work by con and colleagues
where they make it modular and easy to
use but made for theoretical simulations
only and I think this summer they just
finished Jack's reimplementation of pp
which means now you can also use it to
fit to
behavior but it's not
designed wasn't primarily designed for
that and um it was also not made for
engineering purposes python is too slow
although I'm sure could in
principle and since then has come the
C++ package right um which is much
faster and I think but hard to use
because it's C although there are
rappers in different languages that
would be useful for machine
learning RX and Fir implements active
inflence and many other things on b
style cograph which is a very efficient
and Powerful way of thinking bent
inference and variation bent inference
and that is optimized much more for
engineering if you want to build
something that does something using
active inference go C++ or
um or RX info
if you want to apply to behavioral data
then go PDP or active inf. JL um and
there are some tools for this also in
metl but I think our package and mdp
are made for to make this easier and as
you might notice we use much of the
syntax from PP so we're heavily inspired
by that and in the next part you will
see how to use it to apply the package
to behavior does that answer those
questions oh yeah perfect definitely the
functions look great and your your
team's understanding and Clarity
around the problem setup taking that all
the way through the helper functions for
the matricies that's where so much of
the friction is so this makes it really
clear it's a great open source
point it's also where a kind of future
development will be also there so the
API can be improved for sure and we will
work on this also to make it because I
think one of the main challenges active
influence has faced as a tool for C
modeling is that it's hard to use and
hard to understand and that's why much
of the mathematical psychology world for
example just leaves it they say we have
a two or three equation model why would
we use your beam of of a mon machine
instead but just as it has been the case
with many other methods making tools
that make it easy to use and
conceptualizations that make it easy to
understand is the kind of thing that
will make these
models um feasible and therefore used
more
building yeah that's that's making me
think like RX and fur is the car factory
this is the bike and active inference is
the
wheel you can think of it
yeah you need the logo
yeah all right let's do the the last
important section and then see how much
time
okay and because we're short in time I
will need to skip through a few of the
sections but I hope it's going to be all
right yeah so I think Peter already
mentioned that we the sort of
environment of packages in Julia and one
of them is uh action models which is
sort of a sister package uh for us which
mediates the data fitting process for us
right so here we are essentially going
in the opposite direction where our
inputs and the the actions of our let's
say experimental subjects uh are known
but now we are interested in the hidden
or latent uh parameters of the
subjective um generative
model um so this a sort of core
component of action models is the action
model function which depending on our on
our model can be an arbitrary function
which takes a single input which in our
case is a single observation it updates
the states of the agent and then it sort
of quantifies the probabilities of
actions so we end up with a probability
distribution from which we can sample uh
our
actions right and so in our case we have
this nice function called action
pmdp um which is our active inference
action model and it takes these two
arguments which is our initialized aif
object with the parameters of the
generative model settings Etc and it
takes the the takes a single observation
and then the out it outputs the action
distribution so in this particular case
we have two action distributions one for
each state
Factor right and then another core
component of action models is an agent
so it sort of wraps our action model
function and our um active inference um
object in more more uh abstract
structure which with the use will be
will be using for fitting and for um
simulation as well and it also stores
parameters States uh history
Etc right now I will just allow myself
to skip through some of the convenience
functions so I can just go straight to
the data fitting if it's all right okay
so um this is I would assume the most
interesting interesting part of this so
how to actually fit active inference uh
models to data so um all all of our
fitting functions kind of operate on
touring and we wrap all of the necessary
touring operations in our convenience
functions for fitting so let's say for
example we want to fit a single subject
and we want to recover a single
parameter this sort of minimal simple
example so we start by specifying the
prior so here let's say we want to
recover our action Precision parameter
Alpha so we set the prior for it let's
say a gan with a mean of six and sigma 2
and set it in dictionary in any casee we
want to put more parameters at once we
just add them to the same dictionary in
their corresponding prior
distributions and so now we can use the
create model function which will
instantiate our probabilistic model on
our data and it takes these uh inputs
which is our initialized agents takes
our priors and our collected
observations and actions which we
collect let's say from from a behavioral
uh experiment and in in this case
uh we're just using some data from
simulated teamas so here we um our
actions um is a matrix which um which
has rows corresponding to time steps or
let's say trials and columns
corresponding to State factors and
similarly in observations uh we have
columns corresponding to Observation
modalities right and then we'll have our
model object instantiated which we can
easily fit in a single line using arit
model function which will run the
sampler with appropriate defaults and
then we can like obviously people would
want to pass some some more specific
settings then to the sampler so here I'm
passing for example uh the number of
iterations per chain and I'm running
four chains and then I'm using the
distributed module to run the chains um
in
parallel right and then we after the
sampling is finished then we will end up
with the results object which which
contains our chains and then we can work
further with this right so here I'm just
going to quickly go through some of our
other convenience functions for example
to rename chains which will rename the
names of the parameters in our chain so
something more more intuitive and we can
extract quantities from our chains so we
can just simply display the results of
of our chain so we can get the summary
statistics some information about about
the conversions of our chains quantal
Etc right or then we can just use the
sort of native jly uploading functions
we can pass our our chains to it uh to
take a look at chain traces or posterior
distributions or we can uh what we can
do is we can sample from our prior so
here I'm taking a th samples from the
prior and I'm I'm using our plot
parameters function to plot um the the
posterior distribution against um
against the prior distribution um for
our um synthetic participant let's
say okay and this is a part is going to
be mostly interesting I think for people
in computational Psychiatry and
cognitive modeling and it's the case
where we want to fit uh full data set so
in this case let's say that we have some
data with 10 participants and let's
assume that we have two clinical groups
um in our data it can be I don't know um
control and um whatever psychotic or it
can be young um
old um right and we can simply pass the
wall data set with our collected um data
let's say from from our behavioral
experiment there same create model
function so instantiates the the
probabilistic model um on the world data
set and then an additional things that
we need to tell the function is which
columns to use to differentiate between
individual subjects and which columns uh
contain our observations and which
columns contain our actions and again we
have our model instantiated on the W
data set and we can just pass it on to
to our fit model
function right and again this following
is sort of the same procedure as before
we can play around with our recovered
chains here we have the the recovered
values of alpha for for each participant
and I'm using um Native J functions to
topl the chain
traces and again we can let's say sample
from the prior and quot the posterior
against prior distributions for each
participant right and then so of keeping
also with the with this default
procedure in cognitive
modeling now let's say that we have our
estimates and we want to see where there
is actually
a difference right in in our two groups
right so here I'm just extracting the
quantities from the chain and I'm
getting the estimates which these case
are medians and we can see here that
there are indeed um two groups present
in our data right and then after let's
say that we run some statistics on our
estimates then we might be also
interested uh to see whether there's any
correlation with other states of our
agent and let's say some physiological
data
here I'm pling the state action
prediction eror reason why people want
to correlate let's say with with brain
data or pupilometry for
example and uh for people who might want
to use variational inference for uh
various reasons over over sampling the
good news is that touring can do
variational inference to so here I just
sort of remade the tutorial which you
can find on the official ing um web page
where I'm in the beginning just
initializing the variational inference
uh algorithm with a sort of default
number of samples and a default number
of iterations and importantly I'm
setting the automatic differentiation
back end to reverse mode automatic
differentiation and then in the vi
function which runs the variational
inference algorithm I'm just reusing our
probabilistic model uh which we have
already created
previously right so this is this is very
nice and what we end up with is our
variational posterior which is a tpe of
distribution so we can sample from it or
work further with
it right and just to rather quickly wrap
up so um we're currently working on the
documentation uh we know it's important
so um it should be done in the next few
weeks let's say uh until then you can
either Reach Out or uh you can refer to
action models documentation which is uh
really nice to wrate
in okay and yeah just briefly just to
summarize what we need to do in our in
our um next potential future uh so we
need to optimize the package is fast but
there are still a lot of things that
need to be improved then the idea was to
for example uh be able to fit all
parameters because for now we we're only
able to to recover the the sort of hyper
parameters or what been called the
non-matrix parameters but in principle
one can also one should be also able to
fit an entire let's say a matrix or C
Matrix which would be really nice and
then okay we can um extend the parameter
learning to all other uh parameters of
the of the generative model and that
idea was to introduce a sort of custom
parameterizations where a user could
introduce a sort of temperature par also
on on on an a matrix and this could be
also in principle then recovered using
data fitting from empirical
data um and lastly I'm just going to say
that um for our fitting we are using
reverse automatic differentiation which
is fast but we are also planning to
start experimenting with other uh
engines which are currently under
development in Chula also which includes
enzyme and moon cake which might be
potentially uh faster and and then on
the side of action models um Peter has
been working for some time also on the
possibility of adding uh linear
regressions so the idea would be that we
could fit the data we could recover our
estimates and we could run linear
regressions with our with our estimates
or with with other um other variables
that we might have in one model yes
which is statistically optimal yes okay
and the last thing we're going to hear
from is that uh when you decide that you
want to start experimenting with our
package and you encounter any issue or
do you have any specific feature in mind
that you wouldd like us to implement
please feel free to your open issue uh
any kind of feedback will be greatly um
appreciated thank you and we're out of
time so I'll I'll just briefly mention
this point that you can treat a whole
group of Agents as one agent and do c
modeling art it's a separate paper so
I'm sure there'll be time to talk about
that at another time to reach out if
that's interesting as well
um yes I think that's it thanks Soul
this is a huge Advance it's really
awesome brings a lot of features a lot
closer to people's hands and
minds and and it's exciting that that
we'll continue developing and learning
about
it thank you okay thank you till next
time time